<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>S. Pauls confidence Deliuered in a sermon before the iudges of assise. By Robert Harris.</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839545</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839545</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02714)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>S. Pauls confidence Deliuered in a sermon before the iudges of assise. By Robert Harris.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Young] for Iohn Bartlet, at the gilt Cup in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Acts XXIV, 16.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Pauls confidence.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his "Six sermons never heretofore published".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>S. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS</hi> CONFIDENCE DELIVERED IN A SERMON before the IVDGES of ASSISE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Harris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN BARTLET, at the gilt Cupin Cheape-ſide, 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3976:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3976:2"/>
            <head>S. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS</hi> CONFIDENCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 24.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And herein doe I exerciſe my ſelfe to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a Conſcience voyde of offence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, and toward men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words read were vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Paul;</hi> the place where, was 1. Caeſarea, 2. the iudgement hall: the time when, when <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull us</hi> the Orator had made a bitter inuectiue againſt him; the manner how, by way of Apologie and Defence, being deepely ſlandered. The order of them is thus: 1. hee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3976:3"/>wipes away the Lawyers aſperſions in particular, 2. giues account of his life in the generall. And here (for here lyes our buſineſſe at this time) he doth two things, 1. he giues vs a ſumme of his Faith, <hi>verſe</hi> 14.15. 2. of his Life, 16. In point of Faith and Profeſſion <hi>Paul</hi> and wee agree, in Life &amp; Practice we are far wide; &amp; therefore we will dwell vpon that this houre. This verſe then containes the briefe and map of <hi>Pauls</hi> life; where firſt note his action <hi>(exerciſe)</hi> Secondly, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of it, <hi>Pauls</hi> ſelfe. Thirdly, the obiect of in <hi>his conſcience.</hi> Fourthly, the end of it, to haue it <hi>voyde of offence</hi> in all caſes, towards all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>For the Firſt, <hi>Pàul</hi> doth, as <hi>Salomon</hi> bids him, ſet his bones to worke, and all his ſtrength. Time hee neither idles nor ſleights, but vſes both dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, skill and conſtancy together;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for all theſe are wrapt vp in his word.</p>
            <p>For the Second, He thought it beſt husbandry to till his owne ground, beſt policie to bee wiſe for himſelfe, and to keepe home; and therefore he takes himſelfe to taske, and becomes his owne Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>And in the third place; becauſe tis as good doe nothing as nothing to the purpoſe, he makes choyce of a good ſubiect to worke vpon <hi>(conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.) Conſcience</hi> is a thing much talked of, but little knowne, and yet leſſe practiſed than vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. I meane not a ſchoole Lecture, or Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3976:3"/>Diſcourſe; yet muſt I expound my Text. <hi>Conſcience</hi> is conſidered two wayes; one way by Philoſophers, another way by Diuines. Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and naturall Learning bring vs thus farre ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the nature of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> i. the Maſters hereof (for the moſt part of them) make the ſoule a building conſiſting of many roomes; ſome higher, ſome lower; whereof the higheſt is the vnderſtanding. This vnderſtanding is either ſpeculatiue, containing ſome generall notions and principles of truth; or practicall, containing the like principles and axiomes of good things: for at the firſt there were (nay ſtill there are) ſome generall principles, belonging partly to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, partly to practice, left in the ſoule of man. Now to this latter, belongs (in their iudgement) <hi>Conſcience,</hi> whoſe office is to reaſon and diſcourſe; and therfore belongs to the vnderſtanding: And its worke lyes about that which is good or bad, at leaſt doable; and therefore belongs to that part or reſpect of the vnderſtanding which is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med practicall.</p>
            <p>In this, there is conſiderable, 1. the nature, 2. the working of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> The nature; ſo they conceit of it, as of a naturall facultie in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding onely or chiefly. For the working, it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhes its owne operations, and driues them to an iſſue by diſcourſe, thus; That which I would not haue done to mee, I muſt not doe to others: I would not haue wrong done to mee;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3976:4"/>therefore &amp;c. This concluſion, is a concluſion of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> &amp; for the premiſſes they haue in their diſtinct diſcourſes ſeuerall termes: but of them enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For Diuines; We may diſtinguiſh them into two fourmes: i. ſome are pen men of holy Writ, ſome only of priuate bookes. Theſe latter are not ſo attentiue to the terme as to the thing; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they call ſometimes the power of ſo reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſomtimes the whole reaſon and ſyllogiſme, ſometimes each propoſition apart, ſometime the effect and conſequent following ſuch an applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and concluſion, by the name of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> But now come to the inſpired Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and there the word is vſed(as other words of like nature in like caſes are) two waies; 1. more ſtrictly and properly, when it is ioyned with other faculties of the ſoule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic.</hi> pro <hi>Cluen.</hi> dixit conſcientiam mentis noſtrae &amp;c.</note> as <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. In the firſt it is differenced from the minde, in the latter from the will. 2. More largely, when tis put alone; and ſo it ſtands for the whole heart, ſoule and ſpirit working inwardly vpon it ſelfe by way of reflexe. So the Hebrewes generally ſpake, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heart, ſpirit, ſoule, conſcience, all one, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the two former. So <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes in his firſt Epiſtle. Thus the word is here vſed, being refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both to God and man. <hi>Pauls</hi> conſcience, heart, and ſpirit, ſound one and the ſame thing in this place; the difference at the moſt is but in the manner of conſidering.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3976:4"/>
            <p> Well, what would <hi>Paul</hi> with his conſcience? he would haue it <hi>voyde of offence:</hi> he would goe an end in the waies of God, without halting, without ſtumbling; for thats his alluſion. A wiſe Traueller, in a rough way, is loth to offend his foot, leſt that offend him: <hi>Paul</hi> is the ſame for his <hi>conſcience;</hi> by no meanes would hee wound that, leſt that ſhould wound him. Hence his ſtudie to keepe his <hi>Conſcience voyde of offence:</hi> Offence 1 ſay, firſt paſſiue: whereby his ſpirit might be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; ſecondly, actiue: whereby his ſpirit might grieue either himſelfe or others vnſeaſonably. This was his ſtudy, &amp; thus inoffenſiue &amp; ſtraight hee would bee with all perſons <hi>(God and Man)</hi> ſo that his <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſhould not bee vpon him for faltring with either, and (in all caſes, by all means, or at all times) as his words may indifferently bee conſtrued.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Thus liued <hi>Paul</hi> at laſt, who was ſo wilde at firſt: why ſhould we deſpaire, hauing the ſame Chirurgian? But of the Words ſo much. Now for Inſtructions: your ſelues ſee many, let me commend the maine vnto you, and binde vp all in this one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Chriſtians muſt haue a ſpeciall care of themſelues, that they doe not in any thing offend their owne conſciences. To keepe the conſcience from offence and hurt, muſt be the taske of euerie Saint. Looke how charie a proude woman is of her beautie, a wiſe man of his eye, a weake man of his ſtomacke; ſo (and much more than ſo)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3976:5"/>ſhould a Chriſtian man be carefull of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of his heart. Will you precept for this? <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpeakes home, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Above all watchings watch the heart &amp;c.</hi> That's the tower that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and Conſcience is one of the Iewels thats there lodged. Will you example? One <hi>Paul</hi> is ſufficient: Hee was once averſe enough, but after conuerſion (in point of faith) hee was all for Chriſt, (in point of life) all for conſcience, <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.28.</note> Will you reaſons? There are enow both for the one and the other, namely, for hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the conſcience firſt; and each man his owne next. For the firſt, we will out of manie cull but two reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Giue the conſcience content and reſt, and it will pay thee a hundred fold, and proue to thee, (next to God its Maſter) the greateſt friend in the world: .i. the trucſt friend; whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are ſometimes too ſhort in reproofes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in comforts; mutter and will not ſpeake out, but thinke more than theyle ſay, and ſay more to others than to thy face; this friend Conſcience (if thou deale friendly with it) will deale friendly with thee. This will round thee in the eare, and ſay, This is well, howeuer it be taken; &amp; therfore be not diſcouraged: this is naught, howeuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded or painted; it is ſtark ſtaring naught, pride, hypocriſie, &amp;c. therefore amend. Ah (brethren!) as no friend lyes ſo neere vs, and can ſound vs ſo well as couſcience, ſo none will deale ſo plainely
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3976:5"/>with vs, if we doe not offend it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſcience is the faſteſt friend in the world. Others goe and come, and ſtand afarre off, now at hand, now I know not where; but conſcience is no ſtarter, its neuer from our fides, out of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes: in rides with vs, it ſits with vs, it lyes with vs, it ſleeps, it wakes with vs: &amp; as it can ſay much from God and of vs, ſo it will if not offended.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſweeteſt friend in the world. A good cheerfull heart (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) is a continuall feaſt. Oh then a ſatisfied and pacified conſcience, what is that? what ioyes be thoſe which will carrie a man out of the earth, and make him ſay, Though I haue wife, children, friends, wealth, houſe, health, eaſe, honour, &amp;c. after my owne heart, yet theſe are nothing to my contentments within? What ioies thoſe that will make one, ſing vnder the Whippe, at the Stake, in the Flames a Oh Conſcience, thou haſt a ſpeciall gift in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting, that canſt make the patient laugh when the ſpectators weepe; and carrie fraile fleſh ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reioycing through a world of bonds, rods, ſwords, racks, wheeles, flames, ſtrappado's! theſe ioyes be ſtrong, vnſpeakcable indeed, this peace paſsing mans vnderſtanding &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The ſureſt friend in the world. Other friends loue not to come to a ſicke mans bedde ſide, or if ſo, they cannot abide to heare his grones, to ſee a dead man, at the moſt they can but follow one to the graue: but Conſcience will make ones bed in ſickneſſe, and cauſe him to lye
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3976:6"/>the ſofter; will ſtand by him when he groanes, and doe him comfort; will hearten him vpon death, when its comming; and ſay, Thy Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer lineth; will whiſper to him when departing; and ſay, Thy warfare is accompliſhed; will lodge the bodre in graue as in a bed; manne the ſoule to heauen, and make him able to looke God in the face without any terrour: So faſt a friend is this, that when riches, husband, parents, friends, breath, life; nay, patience, hope, faith, haue left vs, in ſome meaſure, this will not leaue vs. And would not ſuch a friend, a friend ſo true, firme, kinde, ſure, be much made of; ſhall ſuch a one be offended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ. 2.</hi> The conſcience offended becomes the ſoreſt enemie. The greateſt friends are bittereſt foes when once diuided: no wars to ciuill, to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall warres. The neerer the worſe: and the conſcience is neereſt; and therefore (if an enemy) the heauieſt.</p>
            <p>For this enemy is, 1. vhauoydable. Others may be kept off with ſtrength, or put off with skill: but ſo will not conſcience; no barres, no bolts, no bulwarkes, can keepe that from thy table, thy bed.<note place="margin">Dan. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> may ſooner keepe out ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Medes, than one conſcience: That will paſſe through all his Officers to his Preſence; and in the face of his Nobles and Concubines arrelt him, and ſhake him in deſpight of his ſecuritie. Nor will this watchfull. Officer be bobd with a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3976:6"/>bundle of diſtinctions and cuaſions. When God ſets it on worke, it marcheth furiouſly like <hi>Iohn,</hi> and will take thee vp with his anſwer; What peace ſo long as thy whoredom and ſins remain: As thers no reſpondens like conſcience, ſo no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iector like to that. A man may make a ſhift with a wrangling Sophiſter, with the Diuell himſelfe, better than with his conſcience. For no Diuell knowes that by me, which I doe by my ſelfe: And the conſcience ſhall haue hearing when the Dinel ſhall not; for conſcience is the Kings Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor, and ſpeakes for the great King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This enemie is vnſufferable: it ſtrips vs at one ſtroke of all other comfort. A ſicke ſtomack makes one wearie of his bed, chaire, chamber, houſe, meats, drinks; yea, that meate that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much pleaſed, now encreaſeth his ſickneſſe. So doth a ſicke conſcience; it takes away the rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of all naturall comforts, of all ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes and ordinances; and makes one a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and terrour to himſelfe. 2. it fils one full of horrours and vnhappineſſe. A wounded ſpirit who can beare? the Stone, Goute, Strangury, who can beare? Yes, &amp;c. But when the pillars are ſhaken, that which ſhould beare vp all is wounded, when the heauen's fight againſt a man, and a poure creature muſt wreſtle with infinite inſtice, power, &amp;c. oh how hard is this? The wrath of a King is terrible, the rage of Seas, of Fires, of Lyons, but ſtill here is creature againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3976:7"/>creature, weake to weake; but who knowes the power of Gods anger, <hi>Pſul.</hi> 90? Who can ſtand before that conſuming fire? not Men, not Mountaines, not Angels. The terrours of God and anguiſh of ſpirit caſts the Diuell himſelfe into a frenzic, and makes him mad; nay, a wounded ſpirit made the Heire of all things vtter his griefes in theſe ſad termes (<hi>My God, my God,</hi> &amp;c.) That which a thouſand mockes, tenne thouſand priſons and perſecutions could not haue done; this one alone, when nothing elſe ailed him, was able to effect: and therefore good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon haue we to guard this part, and to giue our ſpirits no occaſion of griefe. And for the firſt, theſe Reaſons ſhall ſerue the turne.</p>
            <p>Now touching the ſecond. Euery man muſt keepe his own vine, and pleaſe his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Why; Hold ſtill whileſt I poure in theſe? Reaſons, becauſe I am in haſte. 1. Tis fit that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one ſhould be beft ſeene in his owne Booke: and tis a thouſand pities, that in this bookth age, this Book of Conſcience is leaſt ſtudied. 2. This is a meare-ſtone that diuides the Chriſtian and the Hypocrite. The Hypocrites knowledge runnes outward and fromward, the Chriſtians lookes inward and reflects vpon is ſalfe: the ones is ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the others conſcience, the one leues to be doing with other mens conſciences, the other with his owne. 3. Heres the triall of a mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. He thats wiſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> will be wiſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3976:7"/>for himſelf, and, The righteous hath care of his owne ſoule. 4. This watching at home, keepes out pride, iudging in buſineſſes abroad, makes one quiet with others, tame in himſelfe, low and baſe before God in his owne eyes. But wee muſt away. 5. He will bee a ſorry Phyſician to others that hath neuer practiſed vpon himſelfe in this kinde, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1. Heres matter of complaint and chiding. I told you at firſt, that weare of <hi>Pauls</hi> Faith, not of his Life. Tis true in this ſenſe: <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſed the truth of Chriſt, ſo doe we; hee called vpon Gods Name, ſo we; he gaue aſſent to the Word written ſo we; hee apprehended a life to come and reſurrection, ſo wee: But now <hi>Paul</hi> dwels, non in proteſtations and ſpeculations; but hee comes to practicew to <hi>conſcianee:</hi> here we leaue him. In this age, conſciecce is vſed as loue is; We ſpend all in words, and ſend it away in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements; we keep none our ſehues; we haue (our. <hi>exerciſes</hi>) now; but they are exerciſes of bodie, of eſtate, of wit, of memorie, of learning, they hee not exerciſes of conſcience. No ſooner can you name the thing before ſome kinde of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, but they are preſently diſputing, What think your. Is conſcience, an act, an babit, or a facultie, or the whole ſoule with its eyes inward? or what is it: They ſpend the time in defining it, rather than, in reſining, and reforming of it. Here of comes it, that when they are ſent for to a ſicke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3976:8"/>reat; they be as farre to ſeeke, as that Phyſician who hath read much, but practiſed nothing: and for the many; once mention conſcience, and they will quickly put you by with a rude Prouerb, That conſcience was hanged a great while agoe. Thus the terme is now growne odious, the thing it ſelfe a meere ſtranger. Certainely, tis few mens exerciſe to ſtudy conſcience; their (owne) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Indeede Flyes are buſie about others ſores, &amp; ſo is the world about others conſciences. Euery one now is a maſter, nay one man is many maſters.<note place="margin">law. <hi>3.1.</hi>
               </note> He will ſit and keepe Court in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a thouſand; Lord it ouer his brethren, his betters; iudging all callings, all profeſſions, all conſciences, but his owne. I will dot ſpend breath vpon ſuch as barke at all good, becauſe they would haue none in the world. I wiſh that all the paines of ſome Profeſſors were not ſpeat in this; euen in rifling others conſciences, rather than their owne. Religion, religion is ſomething elſe than a iudging of other men. After meare, the heate ſhould repayne homeward; not flye as farre off from the heart and ſtomacke, as the body will beare it: and when we haue heard a Sermon of conſcience, we ſhould recoyle vpon our ſelues, with, What haue I done? or, What ſhall I doe? not looke vpon another, and carue all to him; much leſſe flye vpon them who ſtand as farre off vs, as the King hath land. Oh men vnwiſe, who are more troubled with others diſeaſes than their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3976:8"/>owne; and more deſirous of peace in their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſes than at home. Well, <hi>Paul</hi> would haue beene ſorry to ſee his neighbour ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke: but yet hee is moſt chary of his owne veſſell, leſt that ſhould daſh and receine ſome bruiſe: by no meanes would he haue his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence offended. But out vpon ſuch Chriſtians as this age brings forth; feare of man, hope of gain, loue of honour, of caſe, of fauour, will make them run ouer their conſcience and all Gods mounds. Rather than the man will endure the frownes of his Maſter, the wiſe of her husband, the tenant of his Landlord, hee will lye, couſin, ſweare, runne, ride, doe anie thing on the Sabbath: nay, for one pound, ſhilling, groat, penny, you may hyre a man to gaſh his conſcience; ſo little care haue men of giuing it offence. But how farre ſtretches <hi>Pauls</hi> care? To all caſes, to all perſons. To all: To all certainly, at all times: firſt, towards God, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, towards man. Towards God: Marke this all yee Ciuilians, that cry out as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 3. of diſorder, ſo yee of Conſcience, What conſcience, what conſcience? when you are worſt your ſelues. A good conſcience muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with God; you neyther begin nor end there. A mecre carnall ciuill man is all for man, nothing for God: he payes men their owne, liues quietly and fairely to the world-ward, and therefore thinks himſelfe a man of conſcience. But what conſcience is in this, to deale wel with the ſubiect
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3976:9"/>and not with the Prince? What conſcience in breaking the firſt article of agreement betweene God and man, which is, to know him? What conſcience, to dwell in Gods houſe and pay him no rent; to enter into bonds, and neuer thinke of payment; to ſmite God with oathes for mans oft fences; to ſteale away time from God, when hee hath giuen vs much? Shew mee a meere carnall ciuill man that makes conſcience of the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, or fourth Commandement; of ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting knowledge; of ſetting vp God in his houſe; of forbearing an oath; of keeping the Sabbath, &amp;c. Verily, where there is no God, there can be no confidence: And ſuch a man is without God in the world.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, <hi>Pauls</hi> conſcience reacht to men alſo. Let all Profeſſors (as they wilbe called) note this, A good conſcience begins with God, but ends in Man. A conſcionable man, as he muſt be a profeſſor, hearer, louer of the Word, a kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Sabbath, a zealous obſeruer of the firſt Table: ſo muſt he be a peaceable, iuſt, ſober, free, kinde, honeſt man, and deale ſquarely with all men. Thus it ſhould be: But O times, O man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners! now Profeſſion is become loathſome, and, to ſay the truth, the behauiour of many is ſuch, that it would make an vnſettled man call into queſtion all Profeſſion, all Religion, all Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence almoſt. We talke of Conſcience, but where is it: who makes conſcience of his words?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3976:9"/>who of his bargaines? who of his place or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: Euery man cries out of other: but who diſcharges his owne part? Wee haue a ſaying in Gods Book, He that prouides not for his kindred, is worſe than an Infidell. What cares the rich if his poore kinſman ſtarue? We haue a precept, Husbands loue your wiues: What conſcience is made of this? We haue a commandement Speak not euill of the ruler: Wee haue a charge, Doe good againſt euill: A charge, Toyle not to bee rich, Defraud not, Whiſper not, &amp;c. A command, Be rich in good workes: Faſhion not your ſelues to the world: What ſhall's ſay to theſe things? Is there a conſcience at all: Any ceraintie in the Word at all? Any heauen, any hell? What doe we mean thus to ſlubber ouer matters: If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecue nothing, meane nothing in good earneſt, why doe wee diſſemble: why forbeare wee any thing? If we be in earneſt in one comandement, why not in all? If in one thing, why not in euery thing, as <hi>Paul</hi> was? He was ſtill like himſelfe, at all times, in all caſes. We haue our reſerued caſes. One wilbe a Chriſtian, and a man of conſcience: but hee hath his infirmitie; hee doth nor loue his wife. Another will be your hearer: but hee muſt liue by his trade. A third will be your conuert, ſo you will helpe him to aboue ten in the hundred: the iuſt rate he likes not, it ſounds like. Vſurie; but as much aboue as you can, with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. A fourth will gine ſomthing to a Preacher,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3976:10"/>vpon condition he may bear the Preachers purſe, and bee his Farmor. A fifth will ride with you from morning to night; ſo hee may hold his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſtill in other mens ſores. Away, Hypocrites, away, make no mote profeſſion, talke no more of it, till you meane to be honeſter men; either ſhew vs <hi>Pauls</hi> conſcience, or none. If you cannot reach this here; yet you muſt that there, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18. Defire to liue, &amp;c. elſe there is no truth in you, no comfort for you, no heed to betaken of you, downe you will when a little preſt, like a hollow wall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All ye of <hi>Pauls</hi> Profeſſion, vſe this exerciſe, ceaſe from others; beginne with your ſelues; trauell not ſo much for good houſes, good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, good faces, good heads, as for good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; ſeeke not ſo much the fauour of the world, the countenance of Princes, as of your owne conſcience. Here ſtudie, here ſweat, here labour to be throughout blameleſſe. Oh the peace of a quiet and well pleaſed conſcience is great! the boldneſſe of him that hath it, is great; he eats well, ſleepes well, dwels well, liues well, hee is in much ſafety, hee can hold vp his face ioyfully before a world of accuſers. So is not the vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable: Euery buſh is a man, euery man an enemie, euery leafe an executioner. A ſound of feare is in his eares, and the noyſe of troubles makes him aske, Who can ſtand before a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all burning? As for libertie, thats loſt: he muſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3976:10"/>not ſpeak againſt others, leſt they ſtop his mouth: he muſt bee a ſeruant to euery one, of whom hee would borrow a good word. For the purpoſe: Say a man be couetous; how muſt hee crouch to euery one for his word? how many apologies and excuſes muſt he drop at euery doore? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a good conſcience concludes, I haue done my beſt; and now let them ſay their worſt, I will weare it as a Crowne. Well then, ſith ſo many ſweet things be bound vp in conſcience; peace, comfort, courage, libertie; eſteeme it highly, &amp; reſolue with <hi>Paul,</hi> I had rather dye than loſe my reioycing this way. Loſe it if you will not, take vp his exerciſe, and keep it from offence. Which that you may doe, I will ſhew you theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is to offend the conſcience: 2. what be the degrees of this offence: 3. what the means whereby: 4. what the remedies: 5. what the letts in the vſe of theſe remedies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to offend the conſcience, is to trouble the welfare of it. The foot is then offended, when the health of it is impeached, and the exerciſe of it hindered, that either it cannot ſtir at all, or not ſtraightly, and with any eaſe. Thinke the ſame of conſcience: the health of it ſtands in three; 1. in the cleareneſſe of it: 2. in the goodneſſe of it: 3. in the liuelineſſe and ſenſibleneſſe of it; as tis in the eye: the clearneſſe of it is double, 1. op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſed to ignorance and deluſion: 2. to hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and falſeneſſe. The goodneſſe of it ſtands
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3976:11"/>in the quietneſſe and peace of it: And thereto is oppoſed, 1. a troubled conſcience, and, 2. a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed conſcience. The tenderneſſe of the conſcience, is its quickneſſe in apprehending its owne eſtate, and iudging of its owne doings: Whereto is oppoſed 1. a ſleepy, 2. a dead and ſeared conſcience. When any thing is done or left vndone, whereby the cleareneſſe, quietneſſe, or working of the conſcience is any way impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, then conſcience is offended.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the degrees of theſe offences are diuers, as a man may more or leſſe wound his foot againſt a ſtone.<note place="margin">V. notes on Pron. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 1. there is a tempting of the conſcience: when a man vnreſolued of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of a thing, venters vpon it as vpon meat neuer tried before: 2. a wounding of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: when a man for feare, hope, &amp;c. doth a thing againſt knowledge: 3. a killing of it: when he trades in knowne ſins, of purpoſe to paue and brawne his conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The meanes, whereby the conſcience comes to be offended, is double: 1. when we are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it: 2. when wrongfull to it. Wanting, when we doe not watch and ſaue the conſcience, as we doe the eye from duſt. 2. When we do not ſpeedily looke to wounds, if any. If any thing breed in the eye, it may ſoone be loſt: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is a veſſell that muſt bee waſht daily (as dimme eyes bee) and that by Repentance and Faith.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3976:11"/> 3 When wee doe not eſtabliſh the heart and conſcience. A weake childe ſoone ſtumbles, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vpheld; ſo conſcience. This muſt be vpheld firſt, by grace, ſecondly, by conference &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Wrongfull to it; 1. when wee hinder the worke of it: for euery thing delights in acting its owne operations: 2. when we force ſinne vpon it againſt light of nature or grace, eſpecially groſſe ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The remedies: 1. Pacifie it; not by daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing &amp;c. but by Gods meanes. 1. The ſinne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending muſt be reuerſed; as meate that will not be digeſted: it ſticks as an arrow in the fleſh, that muſt be pluckt out by repentance and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2. Chriſts bloud applyed, the onely ſalue for a ſicke ſoule. 2. When reconciled, peace muſt be maintained. Here take theſe rules: 1. do nothing wilfully againſt conſcience; 2. nothing doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly when reſolution may be had; 3. nothing blindely: for meat vnwittingly taken, may after trouble.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Thus you ſee directions. To the end that you may practiſe, remoue 1. letts; which are of two heads: 1. want of will, 2. want of skill. The firſt ariſes from three wants; 1. of faith, as if the courſe were vnprofitable, 2. of loue to Gods truth, man, &amp;c. 3 of truth and vprightneſſe: wee had rather be hypocrites than otherwiſe &amp;c. See all, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. 2. Want of skill; which ariſes 1. from want of vnderſtanding the Word, 2. want
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3976:12"/>of experience, 3. want of exerciſe &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then ſith in this veſſell (Conſcience) lyes all our treaſure, faith, life it ſelfe, &amp;c. therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it well, get ouer all difficulties, helpe faith, loue, truth &amp;c. vſe all meanes &amp;c. follow <hi>Paul</hi> till thou canſt ſay with him, I deſire to keepe a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Apology for ſuch as ſtand vpon Conſcience. Theſe are the worlds fooles; but tis no matter, they are Gods iewels and delight: and when they ſtand, as <hi>Paul,</hi> before the iudgement feat of man, nay of God, they ſhall finde a good conſcience a better breſt-plate and buckler than a world of wealth. Onely be ſure of this; 1. that tis conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. There be two things in the world that look a little like it, but are not conſcience: 1. Cuſtome, which breedes in blinde men, Popiſh perſons, and moſt vnregenerate men, who haue had good bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, a kinde of trouble and regret; which is no more conſcience than the aking of the ſtomacke when it wants its ſet meales. 2. Preiudice and conceit, when a man vpon ſome preſumptions and probabilities hath pitcht vpon a concluſion, (eyther for or againſt a thing) and will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. True Conſcience differs from both theſe: For firſt, that knowes it ground; ſecondly, that ground is ſome Scripture: which becauſe it may bee haply miſtaken, therefore conſcience is euer teachable, as willing to heare as to ſpeake, to lay downe as to take vp an opinion. Not ſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3976:12"/>they are violent if oppoſed, and euery man that thinks not as they thinke, wants iudgement, or truth, or both. 2. This conſcience muſt bee cleere towards God and man, and haue both it eyes. What hath the hypocrite to doe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? A man of conſcience muſt and vſually will be ſuteable and throughout orderly; though I doubt not, but that there is a partiall hypocriſie, as well as ignorance in ſome men at all times, and in all men, euen in Saints, at ſome times. 3. It muſt be our owne conſcience, as <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeaks: and fourthly, to make an end, a good conſcience muſt bee qualified as is heauenly wiſedome (for this is a great part of it,) How is that? St. <hi>Iames</hi> ſhewes it, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.17. 1. pure in it ſelfe, 2. peace, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others and it ſelfe, 3. moderate, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting extremities, 4. teachable and eaſie to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, 5. pitifull and helpefull euery way. And as it muſt haue theſe excellencies, ſo muſt it bee voyde of partialitie in cauſes and perſons; and of hypocriſie betweene God and it ſelfe. And hee that hath ſuch a conſcience, or labours for ſuch with <hi>Pauls</hi> exerciſes, ſhall hold out his profeſsion, and hold vp his face, when a thouſand others ſhall blaſt and wither.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
